Preliminary Inventory to the Grace Nichols Pearson Papers, 1941-1973.
Hoover Institution Archives
Grace Nichols Pearson Papers,
1941-1973.
46003
Pearson, Grace Nichols.
2 manuscript boxes, memorabilia (1 linear foot)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, pamphlets, reports, newspaper articles, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to the evacuation and resettlement of Japanese Americans on the West Coast during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1946.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
American Friends Service Committee.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; United States.
Container List
- General correspondence, 1941-1945. Letters regarding loyalties of Japanese Americans, relocation of Japanese students, and letters from Japanese Americans in the relocation camps in Colorado, Arizona, Utah, and California (Box 1., Folder 1)
- List of correspondents (Folder 2)
- Correspondence, reports, and general information to Miss Nichols from Professor Robert Emerson regarding Guayule Rubber Project at Camp Manzanar, California (for meeting rubber emergency in World War II), 1942. Original paper on guayule rubber production in relocation centers, by Grace Nichols (Folder 3)
- Correspondence between Miss Nichols and Dean Maddox regarding the loyalty of Japanese Americans and Quakers, 1942 (Folder 4)
- Correspondence between Miss Nichols and Bishop G. Bromley Oxnam regarding Nazi domination, conscientious objectors, and Japanese relocation, 1942 (Folder 5)
- Correspondence from Miss Nichols and others to Attorney Frank J. Hennessy in regard to the transfer of Japanese American R. Yokoyama, 1942 (Folder 6)
- Correspondence, questionnaire, and memoranda regarding the religious connections of Wilfred D. Pearson, 1942 (Folder 7)
- Pamphlets, brochures, newspaper clippings, and bulletins regarding Japanese American evacuation and re-settlement (Folder 8)
  - Description of camps at Tanforan, Poston, Topaz, and Tule Lake
  - Educational programs at several location camps
  - Reports
    - "The History of California's Japanese Problem and the Part Played by the Native Sons of the Golden West," by Peter T. Conmy, Grand Historian of the N.S.G.W.
    - "Evacuation of Alien Enemies from West Coast Areas," by Common Council for American Unity
    - "California and Her Less Favored Minorities," by Ruth E. McKee, WRA historian
- Greeting cards, religious church bulletins, and several photographs sent to Miss Nichols by various Japanese Americans in the centers (Box 2., Folder 1)